<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Anson Writes</title>
 <link href="http://blog.mackeracher.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://blog.mackeracher.com/"/>
 <updated>2013-09-25T00:48:24-04:00</updated>
 <id>http://blog.mackeracher.com/</id>
 <author>
   <name>Anson MacKeracher</name>
   <email>amackera@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Climbing and life</title>
   <link href="http://blog.mackeracher.com/2012/01/16/climbing-and-life.html"/>
   <updated>2012-01-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://blog.mackeracher.com/2012/01/16/climbing-and-life</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recently I have started rock climbing. I&#39;m pretty awful at it, but I&#39;m making
solid progress the longer I keep at it the better I get. It&#39;s been a fun and
interesting process learning a new sport through the end of the summer and the
start of the fall. There&#39;s a whole vernacular of technical terms relating to
aspects of the sport; there&#39;s technique to learn, and muscles to build; there
are skills to develop like reading a route and understanding how to distribute
one&#39;s weight. Overall it&#39;s a very pleasing experience to take up something new
and carry through with it at least to an intermediate level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It got me thinking about other hobbies I have on the go. For a long time the
only thing I really did was mess around with computers. I took a silent
pleasure in learning how to deploy a Django app, or compiling my own Linux
kernel. I still do these things, along with playing video games, but I&#39;m
starting to find my focus wandering.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Work like you play</title>
   <link href="http://blog.mackeracher.com/2011/10/01/work-like-you-play.html"/>
   <updated>2011-10-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://blog.mackeracher.com/2011/10/01/work-like-you-play</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have a confession to make: All day I sit at work and program computers,
then after work I go home and do the exact same thing. The programs I
write at work and at home are different (right now at work I&#39;m writing
a beefy Django app with tons of client-site Backbone JavaScript, but at
home I&#39;m learning Rails); but to the untrained eye it must look like I just
tap-tap-tap all my free time away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course I wouldn&#39;t program in my free time unless I thought it was fun.
I pretty much &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; do things that I think are fun. Life&#39;s too
short to spend any time being miserable about what you do. Work is a different
kind of fun though; work is stressful and high-pressure. We have customers
that need features, we have bugs that need fixing &lt;em&gt;yesterday&lt;/em&gt;.
Those factors that make it stressful are also the factors that make it
&lt;em&gt;rewarding.&lt;/em&gt; I know that a good publish will make our users happier,
and that a bad push will make them sad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hacking a Rails app in my spare time is a different beast. Most of my time
is spent reading up on best-practices, reading entertaining blog posts by
characters in the Rails community, and reading the works of the venerable _why.
If I worked at a Rails shop would I still find it as fun? Maybe, maybe not.
Maybe that&#39;s not the point. I have more freedom to write bullet-proof high-quality
code, but if I delay my publish by 2 weeks nobody is going to care (or even notice!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does a lawyer finish work at the office and go home to work on slightly
different lawyer work? Does a doctor? What about a road-worker, a journalist,
a carpenter? I don&#39;t think so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who does keep working after hours? Artists. Musicians. Writers. Creators.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Doubts</title>
   <link href="http://blog.mackeracher.com/2011/04/28/doubts.html"/>
   <updated>2011-04-28T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://blog.mackeracher.com/2011/04/28/doubts</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;The whole problem with the world is that fools and fanatics are always so certain of themselves, but wiser people so full of doubts.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: right;&quot;&gt;- Bertrand Russell&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Real-time Search and The Decentralization of Information</title>
   <link href="http://blog.mackeracher.com/2010/12/25/real-time-search-and-the-decentralization-of-information.html"/>
   <updated>2010-12-25T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://blog.mackeracher.com/2010/12/25/real-time-search-and-the-decentralization-of-information</id>
   <content type="html">Often, in a spare moment alone with my laptop, I find myself watching TED talks. Today I watched a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ted.com/talks/lang/eng/evan_williams_on_listening_to_twitter_users.html&quot;&gt;nervous looking&lt;/a&gt; Evan Williams talk about Twitter, how it grew out of a side project of another company, how they listened to their users in creating useful features such as the @reply.

While watching it struck me that real-time search is a monumental thing. Not just a cool distraction, but a paradigm shift in how we, as humans, might perceive ourselves. Previous to any kind of real-time search we depended on centralized media to deliver current events to us, and that same media would drop its own bias into the information payload. Now, with Twitter, we can disseminate important information instantly, globally, with no bias but our own. Twitter is the decentralization of information delivery.

People often compare Twitter to shouting into a vast emptiness, and at times it can seem that way; however, we aren&#39;t shouting into nothingness, we are shouting at the world. Real-time search is the tool that enables us to listen to what the world is saying.
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Turns out Bose headphones rock</title>
   <link href="http://blog.mackeracher.com/2010/11/19/turns-out-bose-headphones-rock.html"/>
   <updated>2010-11-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://blog.mackeracher.com/2010/11/19/turns-out-bose-headphones-rock</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;div class=&#39;posterous_autopost&#39;&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;http://posterous.com/getfile/files.posterous.com/amackera/09PF6KlnNybIYPUcWoU77WFXFkSsvhliGCT3gDoQsclLhRknu8vqW0a8hG99/IMG_20101119_162651.jpg.scaled.1000.jpg&#39;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://posterous.com/getfile/files.posterous.com/amackera/E8fsBw6PivJNUXVaD0n64E6R5Hs4bvknlSmXuc7o3Dmvc25MfGVvvLC7JADI/IMG_20101119_162651.jpg.scaled.500.jpg&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;377&quot;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>My Life, Drum-roll Please</title>
   <link href="http://blog.mackeracher.com/2010/08/28/my-life-drum-roll-please.html"/>
   <updated>2010-08-28T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://blog.mackeracher.com/2010/08/28/my-life-drum-roll-please</id>
   <content type="html">I haven&#39;t posted on this blog in ages! I have neglected it like many things in my life. Things have been tumultuous for me, these past months, but I&#39;ve emerged from the chaos and I&#39;m doin&#39; fine.

So I am working at a fantastic Waterloo startup &lt;a title=&quot;Top Hat Monocle&quot; href=&quot;http://tophatmonocle.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Top Hat Monocle&lt;/a&gt;, and we&#39;re launching in September. The bulk of my work is top-secret at this time. We don&#39;t want to spoil the punchline too early in the game. Trust me, though, it&#39;s badass.

There&#39;s not much of a point to this post, just writing for the sake of it. Hope everything is well in whatever you folks are up to!
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Why I Became a Pirate</title>
   <link href="http://blog.mackeracher.com/2010/05/08/why-i-became-a-pirate.html"/>
   <updated>2010-05-08T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://blog.mackeracher.com/2010/05/08/why-i-became-a-pirate</id>
   <content type="html">Following a small trend going around in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pirateparty.ca/&quot;&gt;Pirate Party of Canada&lt;/a&gt;&#39;s forums, and specifically Scott Elcomb&#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;http://psema4.com/blog/libertatia.php/2009/09/10/why-i-became-a-pirate&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt;, I have decided to write a small explanation of why I have elected to become a proud Pirate.

Firstly let me make it clear that by &quot;Pirate&quot; I mean a full-fledged, donating &lt;a href=&quot;https://crm.piratepartyofcanada.com/membership_signup.php&quot;&gt;member&lt;/a&gt; of the Pirate Party of Canada. I have &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; become a Somalian bandit who hijacks shipping vessels. I should also clarify that the views expressed here are my own. They are &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; necessarily reflective of the views and opinions of the Pirate Party of Canada. I do not represent the party in any official capacity.
&lt;h3&gt;Don&#39;t Pirates Pillage and Steal?&lt;/h3&gt;
Why would anyone become a Pirate? Pirates have a nasty history of stealing, murdering, and other equally nefarious acts. It is precisely because of this history that certain people have branded information theft as piracy. They associate the negative connotations of piracy with the far less severe crime of downloading a song or movie without paying for it. This enhances the argument that information theft crimes should be met with harsher punishments as a deterrent.

The truth of the matter is that the perpetrators of these crimes are people exactly like you and me. They are not hate-filled creatures hijacking Madonna songs on the high seas. People illegally download music because it&#39;s convenient, and it&#39;s DRM free.

The Pirate Party is taking back the term for the common people accused of these crimes. The powers that be want to brand normal people doing things we all do every day as pirates and criminals. The Pirate Party will take that label and champion it for the very people it was meant to incarcerate.
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Using Django on Dreamhost</title>
   <link href="http://blog.mackeracher.com/2009/10/01/using-django-on-dreamhost.html"/>
   <updated>2009-10-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://blog.mackeracher.com/2009/10/01/using-django-on-dreamhost</id>
   <content type="html">I am in the process of migrating all my websites from &lt;a title=&quot;Pair Networks&quot; href=&quot;http://www.pair.com/&quot;&gt;Pair&lt;/a&gt; hosting to &lt;a title=&quot;Dreamhost&quot; href=&quot;http://dreamhost.com/&quot;&gt;Dreamhost&lt;/a&gt;. I managed to get a deal from Dreamhost that I couldn&#39;t refuse, and I&#39;ve been meaning to redesign some of my projects on top of the &lt;a title=&quot;Django Project&quot; href=&quot;http://www.djangoproject.com/&quot;&gt;Django framework&lt;/a&gt;, so the switch made sense.

Setting up Django projects on Dreamhost isn&#39;t &lt;em&gt;completely&lt;/em&gt; painless, however. The &lt;a title=&quot;Dreamhost Wiki page on Django&quot; href=&quot;http://wiki.dreamhost.com/Django&quot;&gt;wiki article&lt;/a&gt; is very helpful, but if you&#39;re a Django newbie like myself you may get hung up on a few things (like I did). The following is a short tutorial on how to get up and running with Django, with hosting from Dreamhost.
&lt;h3&gt;Getting ready&lt;/h3&gt;
Enable FastCGI in your Dreamhost Web Panel under Domains » Manage Domains » (click the domain to be Django-ified):

[caption id=&quot;attachment_95&quot; align=&quot;aligncenter&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; caption=&quot;Here is where you want to enable FastCGI&quot;]&lt;img class=&quot;size-medium wp-image-95&quot; title=&quot;FastCGI&quot; src=&quot;http://thesplitbrain.com/wp-content/uploads/2009/05/picture-1-300x133.png&quot; alt=&quot;Here is where you want to enable FastCGI&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; height=&quot;133&quot; /&gt;[/caption]

Create a &quot;media&quot; subdomain under Domains » Manage Domains (ex: media.&amp;lt;yourdomain&amp;gt;.com). The media subdomain is where all of your static media files (like images or CSS files) are located. To use these in your Django templates hard-link to the location of the media subdomain (don&#39;t worry we&#39;ll get to this later).

SSH into your Dreamhost server and create a projects directory in your home folder.
&lt;pre lang=&quot;shell&quot;&gt;mkdir django_projects&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Getting and Installing Django&lt;/h3&gt;
Once you have set up your environment you&#39;re ready to go. Get the most recent stable release of Django&#39;s source code through SVN:
&lt;pre lang=&quot;shell&quot;&gt;svn co http://code.djangoproject.com/svn/django/trunk/ django_src&lt;/pre&gt;
This grabs the current release of the Django source code and checks out a working copy to a newly created directory &quot;django_src&quot;. Next we must &quot;install&quot; Django by adding it&#39;s script locations to our PATH variable. The PATH variable is checked by your shell every time you invoke a command (ex &quot;ls&quot; or &quot;mkdir&quot;). Once we add the Django scripts to our PATH we can execute them in our shell. To do this use your favourite text editor to open up ~/.bash_profile. Add the following lines at the bottom of the file:
&lt;pre lang=&quot;shell&quot;&gt;export PATH=$PATH:$HOME/django_src/django/bin
export PYTHONPATH=$PYTHONPATH:$HOME/django_src:$HOME/django_projects&lt;/pre&gt;
Now that we have included the new directories in our PATH (and our PYTHONPATH, Python&#39;s own special PATH variable), you must update your current shell session to reflect the changes. To do this either close and reopen your shell session, or just type:
&lt;pre lang=&quot;shell&quot;&gt;source ~/.bash_profile&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Creating your Django project&lt;/h3&gt;
The next step is to actually start and configure our Django project! To do this navigate to your django_projects directory created earlier, and start your Django project (replace &quot;myproject&quot; with your new project&#39;s intended directory name:
&lt;pre lang=&quot;shell&quot;&gt;cd ~/django_projects
python django-admin.py startproject myproject
chmod 600 myproject/settings.py&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Writing an FCGI Dispatcher&lt;/h3&gt;
Inside of the directory where your website lives, download this handy FCGI dispatched script written by a generous member of the Dreamhost community:
&lt;pre lang=&quot;shell&quot;&gt;cd ~/[your domain]
wget http://svn.saddi.com/py-lib/trunk/fcgi.py&lt;/pre&gt;
Create a new file called &quot;dispatch.fcgi&quot; and fill it with the following:
&lt;pre lang=&quot;shell&quot;&gt;#!/usr/bin/python2.4
import sys
sys.path += [&#39;/home/myuser/django_src&#39;]
sys.path += [&#39;/home/myuser/django_projects&#39;]
from fcgi import WSGIServer
from django.core.handlers.wsgi import WSGIHandler
import os
os.environ[&#39;DJANGO_SETTINGS_MODULE&#39;] = &#39;myproject.settings&#39;
WSGIServer(WSGIHandler()).run()&lt;/pre&gt;
Make sure you change the paths to be the directories you defined earlier! This is very important. Next make the newly created files executable:
&lt;pre lang=&quot;shell&quot;&gt;chmod 755 ~/mydomain.com/dispatch.fcgi ~/mydomain.com/fcgi.py&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Make yourself an .htaccess file&lt;/h3&gt;
Edit ~/[your domain]/.htaccess and add the following:
&lt;pre lang=&quot;shell&quot;&gt;RewriteEngine On
RewriteBase /
RewriteRule ^(dispatch\.fcgi/.*)$ - [L]
RewriteRule ^(.*)$ dispatch.fcgi/$1 [L]&lt;/pre&gt;
Initialize your Django project&#39;s database:
&lt;pre lang=&quot;shell&quot;&gt;~/django_projects/myproject/manage.py syncdb&lt;/pre&gt;
Now you should be able to point your browser to www.&amp;lt;your domain&amp;gt;.com and see the &quot;It worked!&quot; page. You&#39;re all set with your new Django-powered host.
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Books Which Have made a Difference in my Life</title>
   <link href="http://blog.mackeracher.com/2009/09/23/books-which-have-made-a-difference-in-my-life.html"/>
   <updated>2009-09-23T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://blog.mackeracher.com/2009/09/23/books-which-have-made-a-difference-in-my-life</id>
   <content type="html">I do a lot of reading and like many hackers the books I read tend to come from all different genres and eras. I don&#39;t claim to have any profound ability to find good literature, but occasionally in my word wanderings I stumble upon a mind-blowing book which alters the way in which I view the world. Hopefully some kindred spirits will find my annotated list and be encouraged to borrow these books from their library and get reading!

&lt;em&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/em&gt;: The order of this list is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; indicative of their precedence!
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;Siddhartha&lt;/em&gt; by Hermann Hesse&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Siddhartha &lt;/em&gt;perhaps deserves first place (in a list which I &lt;em&gt;just &lt;/em&gt;told you had no order!) since it has so profoundly changed my thinking. The short book depicts the spiritual journey and life of a man living in India at the time of the Buddha. Hermann Hesse&#39;s words struck such a chord that even after two years this book resonates within my thoughts and actions.
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;Godel Escher &amp;amp; Bach&lt;/em&gt; by Douglas Hofstadter&lt;/h3&gt;
GEB, as it&#39;s affectionately called by its fans, is a fascinating romp though the peculiarities of the universe. It is told through a strange sort of partially dialectic, partially ordinary style. Hofstadter&#39;s love of language, words, riddles, and double-meanings shines though in some of the particularly involved puzzles subtly sprinkled throughout the pages of this tome. I recommend this book to any curious individual (not for the faint of heart!).
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Art of Computer Programming&lt;/em&gt; by Donald Knuth&lt;/h3&gt;
How can any hacker&#39;s library be complete without these wonderful manuals by the inventor of &#39;Big O&#39; himself, Donald Knuth. The elegance of the intellect behind these books is evident from, among many things, the meticulous typography, the exercises, and of course the majestic content of the book itself.
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;I, Robot&lt;/em&gt; by Isaac Asimov&lt;/h3&gt;
Science fiction literature was irrevocably changed by the publishing of &lt;em&gt;I, Robot&lt;/em&gt; by Isaac Asimov. Previously the artificial intelligent beings would be wooden, perfectly obeying slaves to their carbon-based masters; however, &lt;em&gt;I, Robot&lt;/em&gt; explored the concept of robots developing a personality, a soul even. In reality, I think, &lt;em&gt;I, Robot&lt;/em&gt; is less about robot psychology and more about examining human psychology through the mirror of our own creation, but the concept that A.I could one day be as powerful, or more powerful, than man has stuck. &lt;em&gt;I, Robot&lt;/em&gt; is absolutely required reading for any science fiction fan.
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;A People&#39;s History of the United States &lt;/em&gt;by Howard Zinn&lt;/h3&gt;
What a masterpiece! This book hit me at a cynical time in my life, fresh off the 2nd Bush election, where my world-view was being ransacked by consistently contrary evidence to my optimism. &lt;em&gt;A People&#39;s History&lt;/em&gt; did nothing to alleviate these misgivings, and indeed reinforced my completely cynical outlook on life! In &lt;em&gt;A People&#39;s History&lt;/em&gt;, Howard Zinn presents a history not from the perspective of generals and presidents, but from striking miners, starving farmers, blacks fighting for their rights, women fighting for equality. The anecdotal evidence may be skewed, but the recurring themes are almost impossible to ignore. The new American aristocracy desires something (cotton, farmland, oil), then they posture America into a position for war, rowl up the population, and send the poor people to die in the name of national duty. It&#39;s a disturbing exposé of the political motivations behind conflict, and the veil pulled over the eyes of the public.
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;Frankenstein&lt;/em&gt; by Mary Shelley&lt;/h3&gt;
This book is the ultimate gothic novel. Through &lt;em&gt;Frankenstein&lt;/em&gt;, Shelley examines the power within man to produce his own destroyer. We arrogantly pursue our desires with no thought to their consequences, and what responsibility do we have once we have unleashed our creation onto the world? Does Frankenstein have the right to pursue the creature and destroy it? Does the creature have the right to live its life? Where does a creator&#39;s power end over his creation?
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;Alias Grace &lt;/em&gt;by Margaret Atwood&lt;/h3&gt;
Though many of my classmates despised this book, I believe it to be an exceptional example of superb creative writing. The great thing about &lt;em&gt;Alias Grace&lt;/em&gt; is that each person who reads it could conclude completely different things about the book&#39;s happens. This ambiguity touches every aspect of the book, and can have a transformative effect on the person&#39;s opinion of its characters. &lt;em&gt;Alias Grace&lt;/em&gt; deserves some serious thought after its conclusion.
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>APN settings for HTC Dream on Rogers</title>
   <link href="http://blog.mackeracher.com/2009/06/27/apn-settings-for-htc-dream-on-rogers.html"/>
   <updated>2009-06-27T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://blog.mackeracher.com/2009/06/27/apn-settings-for-htc-dream-on-rogers</id>
   <content type="html">If any G1 or Dev phone users are trying to get data in Canada, the following is the default APN setting on my Rogers HTC Dream:

&lt;pre lang=&quot;make&quot;&gt;Name: Rogers
APN: rogers-core-appl1.apn
Proxy: not set
Port: not set
Username: not set
Password: not set
Server: not set
MMSC: http://mms.gprs.rogers.com
MMS proxy: 10.128.1.69
MMS port: 80
MCC: 302
MNC: 720
APN Type: not set
&lt;/pre&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Microcontroller Porn</title>
   <link href="http://blog.mackeracher.com/2009/06/14/microcontroller-porn.html"/>
   <updated>2009-06-14T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://blog.mackeracher.com/2009/06/14/microcontroller-porn</id>
   <content type="html">Okay, so it&#39;s not &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; porn since the IC casings are still firming in place, hah. Here are some photos of my Arduino Duemilannove and its Ethernet shield.

First the Duemilannove itself. Sporting the Atmel ATMega168 microcontroller, this is one serious piece of power-efficient hardware. I am currently sketching out a really small Operating System for this board, for kicks and giggles.

[caption id=&quot;attachment_126&quot; align=&quot;aligncenter&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; caption=&quot;The Duemilannove in all its glory&quot;]&lt;a href=&quot;http://thesplitbrain.com/wp-content/uploads/2009/06/2009-06-14-222859.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;size-medium wp-image-126&quot; title=&quot;2009-06-14-222859&quot; src=&quot;http://thesplitbrain.com/wp-content/uploads/2009/06/2009-06-14-222859-300x225.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The Duemilannove in all its glory&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; height=&quot;225&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;[/caption]

[caption id=&quot;attachment_125&quot; align=&quot;aligncenter&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; caption=&quot;A better view of the microcontroller IC&quot;]&lt;a href=&quot;http://thesplitbrain.com/wp-content/uploads/2009/06/2009-06-14-222742.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;size-medium wp-image-125&quot; title=&quot;2009-06-14-222742&quot; src=&quot;http://thesplitbrain.com/wp-content/uploads/2009/06/2009-06-14-222742-300x225.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A better view of the microcontroller IC&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; height=&quot;225&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;[/caption]

Finally the Ethernet shield. My plan is to implement some fairly serious network stackage with this hardware after my OS is stable.

[caption id=&quot;attachment_127&quot; align=&quot;aligncenter&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; caption=&quot;Networking and beyond!&quot;]&lt;a href=&quot;http://thesplitbrain.com/wp-content/uploads/2009/06/2009-06-14-223018.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;size-medium wp-image-127&quot; title=&quot;2009-06-14-223018&quot; src=&quot;http://thesplitbrain.com/wp-content/uploads/2009/06/2009-06-14-223018-300x225.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Networking and beyond!&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; height=&quot;225&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;[/caption]

Check out the Arduino &lt;a title=&quot;Arduino project page&quot; href=&quot;http://www.arduino.cc/&quot;&gt;project page&lt;/a&gt; for details about the hardware. Check out the &lt;a title=&quot;AVR Libc Home Page&quot; href=&quot;http://www.nongnu.org/avr-libc/&quot;&gt;AVR  Libc home page&lt;/a&gt; for details on how to get gcc talking in AVR instructions.

Contact me if you are interested in OS design or just for interest sake.
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Don Quixote</title>
   <link href="http://blog.mackeracher.com/2009/06/12/don-quixote.html"/>
   <updated>2009-06-12T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://blog.mackeracher.com/2009/06/12/don-quixote</id>
   <content type="html">What&#39;s the deal with all the crazy depressed people wandering around in the wasteland in Miguel de Cervantes &lt;em&gt;Don Quixote&lt;/em&gt;? There are seriously uncountable numbers of them. If somebody were to go crazy and wander around aimlessly in the wilderness near my hometown in Canada, they would die before they met anybody interesting.

That is all.
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>What is the brain computer analogy?</title>
   <link href="http://blog.mackeracher.com/2009/05/13/what-is-the-brain-computer-analogy.html"/>
   <updated>2009-05-13T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://blog.mackeracher.com/2009/05/13/what-is-the-brain-computer-analogy</id>
   <content type="html">If you search for &quot;&lt;a title=&quot;Google search for &amp;quot;brain computer analogy&amp;quot;&quot; href=&quot;http://www.google.ca/search?q=brain+computer+analogy&quot;&gt;brain computer analogy&lt;/a&gt;&quot; on Google, you will see, surprisingly, that my &lt;a title=&quot;Comments: What’s missing from the brain-computer analogy&quot; href=&quot;http://thesplitbrain.com/2009/02/09/comments-whats-missing-from-the-brain-computer-analogy/&quot;&gt;comments&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a title=&quot;Encephalogue on Blogger&quot; href=&quot;http://encephalogue.blogspot.com/&quot;&gt;Encephalogue&lt;/a&gt;&#39;s original &lt;a title=&quot;What&#39;s missing from the brain-computer analogy&quot; href=&quot;http://encephalogue.blogspot.com/2008/12/whats-missing-from-brain-computer.html&quot;&gt;ruminations&lt;/a&gt; on the topic appear in &lt;em&gt;pretty high up there &lt;/em&gt;(currently 5th place). How is it that &lt;em&gt;my lowly conjecture&lt;/em&gt; is one of the top Google hits? It boggles me that such a fundamental concept is so underrepresented on the web, so let me remedy that with the following:

The brain-computer analogy (BCA) is simply this: &lt;em&gt;The brain is essentially a computer.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Aren&#39;t computers are made of silicon!?&lt;/h3&gt;
The BCA is not saying that brains are made from the same physical materials as your laptop, or even that the brain functions in similar ways to a computer. The analogy is saying that computers and brains to the same job---they &lt;em&gt;compute things&lt;/em&gt;. In the words of Paul Thagard:
&lt;blockquote&gt;Here is the central hypothesis of cognitive science: Thinking can best be understood as representational structures in the mind and computational procedures that operate on those structures.
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: right;&quot;&gt;- Mind: Introduction to Cognitive Science, MIT Press, 2005.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
In computers, the representational structures mentioned by Thagard are the structures in the computer&#39;s memory, and the computational procedures are the instructions and algorithms used to manipulate those structures. The brain may not have memory that behaves like a computer&#39;s RAM, nor does it likely have algorithmic-like instructions, but the analogy simply assumes that &lt;em&gt;however&lt;/em&gt; the brain does it, the processes in the brain result in the successful computation of incoming data.
&lt;h3&gt;But I don&#39;t feel like a computer!&lt;/h3&gt;
Many people have criticised the BCA for a variety of valid reasons. Chris Chatham over at &lt;a title=&quot;Develoong Intelligence&quot; href=&quot;http://scienceblogs.com/developingintelligence/&quot;&gt;Developing Intelligence blog&lt;/a&gt; came up with&lt;a title=&quot;10 Important Differences between Brains and Computers&quot; href=&quot;http://scienceblogs.com/developingintelligence/2007/03/why_the_brain_is_not_like_a_co.php&quot;&gt; 10 important differences&lt;/a&gt; between brains and computers. Chatham&#39;s concerns are largely based on taking the analogy too far; that is, when people confuse the physical processes found in computers to be analogous to the physical processes in the brain. Indeed, the ways in which brains appear to process information could not be further from the method by which computer&#39;s process information (in terms of the physical processes underlying computation).

For instance computers utilize a simple binary encoding of information whereas the brain&#39;s encoding mechanisms are inherently more complex (timing of neuron spikes or rate at which neurons spike). Even further, the information encoding methods employed by the brain can be even more complex than simple scalar values, representing time-varying stimuli, or even functional representations in many dimensions (Anderson, Eliasmith, 2002).

Also neurons are highly complex machines, displaying high degrees of non-linearity in both the encoding process and transformations on encodings. Computer transistors are also complex machines (and inherently non-linear); however, neurons and transistors are &lt;em&gt;nothing alike&lt;/em&gt; in form or function.
&lt;h3&gt;Is the analogy a good one?&lt;/h3&gt;
What is important in the BCA is not drawing conclusions of the physiology of brain cells or their encoding mechanisms; but rather extending the science of computation into the realm of the brain. If we tear down the analogy between the computer and the brain we pull a mystical veil over the inner workings of the organ. We &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; work in the context of computation to even begin to understand the processes in the brain.

The analogy may seem overly ambitious to many, but the essence of the analogy still stands, 50 years after the field of Cognitive Science was born.
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Brightening My Worldview</title>
   <link href="http://blog.mackeracher.com/2009/04/11/brightening-my-worldview.html"/>
   <updated>2009-04-11T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
   <id>http://blog.mackeracher.com/2009/04/11/brightening-my-worldview</id>
   <content type="html">Having recently admitted by disillusionment with religion to my (religious) parents, I have been finding myself somewhat lost and lonely. Even though for years I had been questioning my faith, and slowing drawing away from identifying with any religious beliefs, I was still part of a community that knew me and liked me. Now I&#39;ve cut that part out of my life. It feels strangely empty and liberating. I feel more genuine since I don&#39;t have to participate in a sham I don&#39;t believe in, but it also feels like I&#39;ve turned my back on something, well, &lt;em&gt;sacred&lt;/em&gt;.

Today I learned of the &lt;a title=&quot;The Brights&#39; Net&quot; href=&quot;http://www.the-brights.net/movement/&quot;&gt;Brights&lt;/a&gt; movement. The movement is for people with a worldview &quot;free of supernatural and mystical forces.&quot; Some heavyweight, vocal intellectuals whom I admire are said to be supporters of the movement (Daniel Dennet, Steven Pinker, Richard Dawkins, among others).

I am glad there is a movement for rational, clear thinkers who possess no room for mysticism in their hearts. I am proud to identify with this movement. Today I call myself a Bright!
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Comments: What's missing from the brain-computer analogy</title>
   <link href="http://blog.mackeracher.com/2009/02/09/comments-whats-missing-from-the-brain-computer-analogy.html"/>
   <updated>2009-02-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://blog.mackeracher.com/2009/02/09/comments-whats-missing-from-the-brain-computer-analogy</id>
   <content type="html">A new blogger over at &lt;a title=&quot;Encephalogue&quot; href=&quot;http://encephalogue.blogspot.com/&quot;&gt;Encephalogue&lt;/a&gt;, Sean Patrick, has posted &lt;a title=&quot;What&#39;s missing from the brain-computer analogy&quot; href=&quot;http://encephalogue.blogspot.com/2008/12/whats-missing-from-brain-computer.html&quot;&gt;his opinions&lt;/a&gt; on the brain-computer analogy, one of the foundations of the cognitive sciences.

It&#39;s a solid read, a good introduction to the dialogue surrounding the mind-machine metaphor. Patrick argues that:
&lt;blockquote&gt;The biggest discovery in neuroscience won&#39;t be the anatomy of the brain, or the physiology of the neuron - it will be the information theory of the mind.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
I&lt;em&gt; mostly&lt;/em&gt; agree with this comment. The information processing properties of the brain are, indeed, the reason why we study the thing. Without data processing the brain is nothing more than a bunch of energy-hungry cells. In fact, one of the most hard-hitting criticisms of neuroscience in recent years has been that the field is &lt;a title=&quot;Jeff Hawkin&#39;s on Neuroscience&quot; href=&quot;http://www.ted.com/index.php/talks/jeff_hawkins_on_how_brain_science_will_change_computing.html&quot;&gt;data&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a title=&quot;Redwood Neuroscience - Mission statement&quot; href=&quot;https://redwood.berkeley.edu/wiki/Mission_and_Research&quot;&gt;rich&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a title=&quot;Computational Neuroscience&quot; href=&quot;http://ctn.uwaterloo.ca/about/abouttheoneuro.html&quot;&gt;theory&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a title=&quot;General theory on complex neural ensembles&quot; href=&quot;http://compneuro.uwaterloo.ca/research.html&quot;&gt;poor&lt;/a&gt;. Where I disagree with Patrick is in the details---I feel that the physiology of neurons and the interactions between neuron populations together hold the key to the coveted information theory!

If a scientist had no understanding of how a computer works, fundamental to &lt;em&gt;gaining&lt;/em&gt; that understanding is determining how transistors function; however, as any competent hardware engineer will tell you, understanding the transistor does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; mean you understand a circuit! An engineer must &lt;em&gt;analyze&lt;/em&gt; a circuit and reach conclusions based on the interactions of the circuit&#39;s elements. Extend the computer metaphor to the brain. We must devour physiological research about neurons, we must consume research about neural networks and maps. &lt;em&gt;Then&lt;/em&gt; we can begin to theorize with any coherency about the information processing abilities of the brain.

However, I&#39;m glad there are other rationalists like &lt;a title=&quot;Encephalogue&quot; href=&quot;http://encephalogue.blogspot.com/&quot;&gt;Sean Patrick&lt;/a&gt; out there---mystical interpretations of brain function are all too common. Welcome abord the blogging train, &lt;a title=&quot;Encephalogue&quot; href=&quot;http://encephalogue.blogspot.com/&quot;&gt;Encephalogue&lt;/a&gt;!
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Programming the Arduino</title>
   <link href="http://blog.mackeracher.com/2009/02/05/programming-the-arduino.html"/>
   <updated>2009-02-05T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://blog.mackeracher.com/2009/02/05/programming-the-arduino</id>
   <content type="html">uC Hobby has an excellent article on &lt;a title=&quot;Programming the Arduino&quot; href=&quot;http://www.uchobby.com/index.php/2009/02/01/mcu-programming-intro-series-1-sos-on-the-arduino/&quot;&gt;programming on the Arduino&lt;/a&gt; platform. I have a particular interest in this since I own and program one of this suckers for fun.

Check it out if you&#39;re interested in learning about microcontroller programming! The Arduino is a great (and cheap) starting point.
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>What is a Turing machine?</title>
   <link href="http://blog.mackeracher.com/2009/02/01/what-is-a-turing-machine.html"/>
   <updated>2009-02-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://blog.mackeracher.com/2009/02/01/what-is-a-turing-machine</id>
   <content type="html">If you have a budding interest in computer science, but have not yet studied it formally, then you&#39;ve likely heard the term &quot;Turing machine&quot; floating around in your adventures across the Internet. Mayhap you have asked yourself &quot;What is this Turing Machine, and why should I care? &quot; eyes wide with wonder and excitement. If so, hopefully this article will offer a modicum of enlightenment; a grain of knowledge.
&lt;h3&gt;Turing machines, what are they?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;a title=&quot;Wikipedia - Turing Machine&quot; href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turing_machine&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; says:
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Turing machines&lt;/strong&gt; are basic abstract symbol-manipulating devices which, despite their simplicity, can be adapted to simulate the logic of any computer algorithm.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
If this doesn&#39;t make any sense to you, but you&#39;re still interested, then great! You&#39;ve come to the right place---sally forth, intrepid reader!

Picture in your brain a big book with many blank pages. This book is our abstract Turing machine! Our machine is quite boring at the moment, wouldn&#39;t you agree? We are about to make it much more exciting, but first we should go over all the things in the fancy Wikipedia definition, and make sure our &quot;Big Book&quot; Turing machine has everything it needs.
&lt;h4&gt;What are symbols?&lt;/h4&gt;
A symbol is any piece of information used by the computer to do computation. In the computer you are using right now, the symbols are strings of ones and zeros stored in your RAM or on your hard disk. In an abstract Turing machine, the symbols in question could be anything we want (like hieroglyphics, the Roman alphabet, or pictures of cats). These symbols may mean something to you or I, but to the Turing machine they are just distinct packets of information. In our &quot;Big Book&quot; Turing machine, to add symbols just imagine some of the blank pages filled with letters and words (written in pencil!).
&lt;h4&gt;Using symbols&lt;/h4&gt;
Symbols are used by our Turing machine in a fancy process called &lt;strong&gt;symbol manipulation&lt;/strong&gt;. This process is the act of changing a symbol in a certain location to an alternative symbol. In our &quot;Big Book&quot; Turing machine, we carry out symbol manipulations by erasing existing letters or hieroglyphics and writing in new ones.
&lt;h4&gt;Instructions&lt;/h4&gt;
In order to know what symbols to erase, and what symbols to write down, we keep list of instructions in a &lt;strong&gt;table&lt;/strong&gt;. Here is an example of an instruction table to give you a better idea of what they accomplish:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;1: If the third symbol on page 31 is a letter &#39;X&#39;, replace it with a letter &#39;Y&#39;.
2: If the fourth symbol on page 28 is a letter &#39;Y&#39;, replace it with a letter &#39;Z&#39;.&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
Where &#39;X&#39; and &#39;Y&#39; are abstract symbols---meaning they are two distinct packets of information.
&lt;h4&gt;States&lt;/h4&gt;
The last piece of the puzzle we need to include in our &quot;Big Book&quot; Turing machine is the concept of &lt;strong&gt;states&lt;/strong&gt;. The state of the Turing machine is an arbitrary attribute which is used to dictate the machine&#39;s behavior. Think of a Turing machine&#39;s states like a person&#39;s state of hunger. When you are in the HUNGRY state you go and look for food to put in your belly. When you are in the JUST-FINISHED-EATING state you do not seek out food. How hungry you are (what state you are in) determines your actions (whether you seek food or not). In a Turing machine we may have arbitrary states Q1 and Q2. Our table of instructions can use these states in the following manner:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;1: In state Q1, if the third symbol on page 31 is &#39;X&#39;, replace it with &#39;Y&#39;; otherwise replace it with &#39;Z&#39;.
2: In state Q2, if the fourth symbol on page 42 is &#39;Y&#39;, replace it with &#39;Z&#39;; otherwise replace it with &#39;X&#39;.&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
We can use this state information to make our symbol manipulation more robust. For instance, we can &lt;em&gt;transition between states&lt;/em&gt; as a way to keep track of what our machine has accomplished so far. Here is a simple program illustrating a state change, and how hey can be useful:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;1: In state Q1, add symbol &#39;X&#39; to symbol stored in &#39;loc&#39;; store result in location &#39;loc&#39;
2: If symbol in &#39;loc&#39; is greater than 10, transition to Q2
3: If state Q1, go to instruction 1
4: If state Q2, FINISH&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
This instruction table adds the values o the symbols &#39;X&#39; and the symbol stored in &#39;loc&#39;, then stores the result itself in location &#39;loc&#39;. Then it tests to see if the result is greater than 10. If the result is less than 10, it repeats the process; if the results is greater than 10 we transition from Q1 to Q1 to indicate that we have finished execution.

Hopefully you can see from this simplistic example that states &amp;amp; state transitions are greatly useful!
&lt;h4&gt;Adapting any algorithm&lt;/h4&gt;
In our &quot;Big Book&quot; Turing machine, imagine a set of instructions complex enough to describe every step in the process of converting the entire text of Ray Bradbury&#39;s &lt;em&gt;Fahrenheit 451&lt;/em&gt; into Isaac Asimov&#39;s &lt;em&gt;Foundation&lt;/em&gt;. Surely this is a complicated task, but given sufficient instructions, paper, time, and motivation, it could be accomplished. This is an example of how we could adapt any conceivable task to be performed by our Turing machine! Instead of using words as symbols, we use bits and bytes inside of a computer---instead of translating books, we can write operating systems and web browsers.
&lt;h4&gt;UTMs, Formality, etc.&lt;/h4&gt;
For those interested in the origin of TMs, you might read the &lt;a title=&quot;Church-Turing Thesis&quot; href=&quot;http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/church-turing/&quot;&gt;Church-Turing Thesis&lt;/a&gt;. For additional information on Universal TMs (TMs which can simulate other TMs), read &lt;a title=&quot;Universal Turing Machines&quot; href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Universal_Turing_machine&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;. Wolfram has a &lt;a title=&quot;A New Kind of Science&quot; href=&quot;http://www.wolframscience.com/nksonline/toc.html&quot;&gt;digitized copy&lt;/a&gt; of his book &lt;em&gt;A New Kind of Science&lt;/em&gt;, which discusses UTMs to some length. Of course, my depiction of a TM is simplistic in order to get the basic idea across. my goal here was to provide a simple, intuitive, allegory of a Turing machine. Computation theory is a very complicated field, and try as I might, I can&#39;t fit its entirety into less than 1000 words.
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The Corpus Callosum</title>
   <link href="http://blog.mackeracher.com/2008/12/08/the-corpus-callosum.html"/>
   <updated>2008-12-08T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://blog.mackeracher.com/2008/12/08/the-corpus-callosum</id>
   <content type="html">The intention behind this blog is to develop and discuss ideas related to the Cognitive Sciences. Potential topics include (but are not limited to): language acquisition and processing, artificial intelligence, computational simulation, consciousness, physiological psychology, philosophy of the mind, computation, and information theory. These are all topics that interest me greatly, and it is my hope that similar minded people will stumble across my writings and find them accessible and engaging.

The Split Brain refers to the outcome of a rare surgical technique called a &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Corpus_callosotomy&quot;&gt;corpus callosotomy&lt;/a&gt;. The patient undergoing surgery has some or all of his or her &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Corpus_callosum&quot;&gt;corpus callosum&lt;/a&gt; severed. The technique is used as a last resort to prevent seizures in serious cases of epilepsy. The corpus callosum is integral in the transmission of information between the left and right hemispheres of the brain. Patients who have undergone a corpus callosotomy display curious behavior, the study of which lead to many advances in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lateralization_of_brain_function&quot;&gt;lateralization of brain function&lt;/a&gt;. I have chosen this name for this blog since it reflects my broad interests. They are seemingly unconnected, yet holistically they are tied together in the interdisciplinary study of Cognitive Science, just as a split-brain patient has two distinct hemispheres, but remains a single conscious entity.

In the coming weeks I will post semi-regularly with my current meditations on some of the topics mentioned earlier. If anyone by chance stumbles across this blog and is interested, comments are welcome and encouraged!
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
